All right, so the next part is show free tests, so shelf top bottoms.
Now, ultimately, where these shelves come in now is, one minute, yeah, so they come in as,
of course, there will be a low time frame, a broader shelf, a broader shelf, further away from price.
Generally, these will be the higher time frame, if this is a higher time frame, price for them.
But ultimately, inside the shelf is the inventory, okay, of the liquidity holding that particular price run up.
So there was the initiation, point in release, skinny leg,
price pause, even to be of residuals sunside, mid-priser on the sunside equity, price pause, bids continue
to absorb it, and then it goes in a continuation leg, okay, inefficiency, it starts to falter,
and then there's a last pop, okay? This is the last drive, this the last pop, okay? Now, once you break
beneath the apex, of course, this could also be considered a shank very close to price, okay?
and also you know depending on the state of liquidity i.e if the top has already been picked
there's unfil liquidity you know we discussed the price can come back in if it extends an
efficiently generated response right back up to the um the apex base now personally i like
taking those trades as well so if the top side was picked there of course this is picking up a nice
level okay it's coming into a nice base higher time bringing off this leg is weaking up
extend down into that level consume the last bit of it okay and then draw back up
I'm unlikely to take that apex retest or the high retest trade okay now there's a few
variables that would increase the probability for me to take this trade okay
this particular trade here sometimes why I'd want it is for price to actually
invalidate the shell okay invalidate the apex coming to nothing pretty
much nothing or like a really lower time frame to take chart one minute chart
fractal pick you up extend the efficient pick you up and draw back up this in here
there's a very high chance and you're taking that trade but of course sometimes
price will come into no man's land extend higher in validating this high if you
take a short there you got stopped but then no that's just part of the game you can
come into like a fractal level and come into a feeding level or a
you can feel liquidity level and generally start dropping off again but we can have a
look at example of that in a minute now once this apex is given in you know you're at your high
end the same thing that happened with price coming back into the the broader shelf okay the broader
shelf is what's going to basically be holding price off it would perpetuate price into a bigger apex
and once you flip these bigger higher time frame shelves it does lead into really big changes
on the state liquidity on the higher time frame that can lead to big price rooms so we
have a look at one okay just for a minute this okay price was sitting on this shelf
there we actually invalidated it very good sign that buyers are drying out yes it actually goes if
we get an apex retest here fine that generates a really big response um we actually end up
invalidating this small shelf by a few pips ticks tens of tens of pips and then it runs again
to brand new highs, okay?
Even though it's doing this, it's running to new highs,
we're draining all the available buy-side liquidity here away.
So if and when this little inventory gave out,
it was very, very clear that price would continue.
It's no surprise then, we get really,
really acceleratory price we went back down
through all this area of wash liquidity.
Okay, that was just pinging off this,
validated it, pinged again, hit this,
this cell side base came into the shelf and validated it run again and you know we just
basically drained all the bi-side liquidity that was holding price up here once we had this
shift occur in the small inventory price did actually end up trending you know since the top of 2018
to now really and all these levels were residual they gave nice responses you know
tradeable responses but ultimately there were left over levels at the middle of the price
now bear me so I'm just going to pull up a picture showing you in what
instance I would actually take the apex test me test tree okay so you see
this example here right this is the shelf on the lower time frame this time
oh not lower time frame 60 minutes we extended and efficiently came into a
level fine pressure dried out what does price do the first thing you actually
does is it slip gaps down okay so this slip gap is the same as this self
similarity you know similar constituent parts anywhere in price that is their
definition of fractal self-similarity price slip-caps down leaving itself
vulnerable to consume the last bit of buy-side liquidity inside this infantry
here this shell what does it do it runs right back off for an apex retest you
better those instances because we're consuming the last bit of liquidity inside
that shell provided this is picking up a nice level which a daily
picked up a daily level and of course the broader you know the broader state of this run
liquidity base price pause which turned into the shell continuation leg high and then the apex
forms using the shelf which is quite close to the apex okay um in those instances depending on
where i expect price to go in this instance it would be down because of just how far extended
the prices, the nature of the state of liquidity and how far this leg came back down to
buy buyers and be willing to take that apex speed test my invalidation would be the
high okay but of course sometimes price will end up extending into a better
level I take the loss but you better go shorter again two tries that's as far as
many tries I'll take and then in this sense that you see pretty much the same
but this time price comes into a mid-price run level pretty much into the middle
nowhere and runs and really extends past this high if I was to have taken this apex retest
short here which I took a short day actually that day I would have got stopped out and I
did get stopped out but the idea still remained valid all this was doing it was draining
liquidity further from this whole price movement and this high which came into this apex
okay it actually ended up trending for 13 days straight it closed down the 13 whole days
So the point I make it here is with your shelf, it's the inventory of liquidity, okay?
The shelf is why stopping price in this instance from dropping straight down.
Hence why price comes into it, okay, the response right back to the apex, sometimes it extend
again for that, that's something called the shelf wash extension, which will cover in the
lap or the video, ultimately is the shelf that is stopping and holding price up.
We need, okay, price to deal off these shelves and absorb them, get through them.
which is going to increase the probability of the trade continuing in one direction.
Sometimes you come right back upon you very, very often, once you flip that shell, you know, all these levels, all these bounces really, they're weak.
The price continues in that direction until it.
This run dries off.
The same thing happens.
Once price, I've sold this inventory, got above it, swing retests at the low.
Again, continued in that direction.
Once price flipped this apex, got beneath this four-hour shelf, which is further away from price,
it actually continued for 13 holes for 12, 13, 11, 10 for a whole trading days.
It was 13 from up there.
So the more you engage, right, when I'm talking about engaging, what you want to be looking at is,
where is the shell, okay?
What is the nature of the unfilled liquidity inside the shell?
Is it on one side or three parts unfilled?
and of course the nature of the leg into the shelf as well is it extending from the high
here into the shelf inefficiently does that then leave it vulnerable is there actually a trade
opportunity if this was a weekly shelf when you'd be able to take a trade it was if this is a daily
shelf would you be able to take a trade and what you'll find is they are actually very very
decent trades inside of the apex bases when they're close sorry inside of the shelves when
they're relatively close to the apex base, okay, because price can come in, grab the unfilled
liquidity, and run it back higher. The same applies for when shelves are quite slightly more
further away from price, but the same applies. Ultimately, what we want is that inefficient
extension to come into the shelf top of the bottom, depending on where the unfold liquidity is,
and we can take that trade. In this instance, I actually wouldn't have taken this because
the unfilled liquidity was at the bottom there. If that extended, I'd completely,
consider taking the apex there, okay, that apex retest,
and maybe the long deer as well, okay?
You can continue to have a look up more examples,
but this is quite definitive,
you know, we don't need to carry on for too long.
Okay, so this is where a shelf
is actually a bit further away from price, okay?
This is your shelf here, all right?
Price extended, ultimately when the shelf was forming there,
we forget all the price action on the right of this box,
When the shelf was forming, it was just a price pause.
So price came into a residual level, not enough liquidity.
It came in, not enough sellers to push price back down.
Not enough sellers to push price back down, bids, trailing around getting sucked up
along with price.
So this was the price pause where they basically, it forced more transactions to occur around this area
because they were pinging off the side liquidity inside that fractal.
So buyers had to carry on transacting.
which ultimately forms a bit of an inventory right right and of course price leaves
residual liquidity behind price extended to the high this is actually a whole cluster there that's
a daily sell-side base price picked up sellers look at the nature of this extension price
pause runs goes into a bit of a consolidation apex and then there's the last parabolic pop
that's where i like to go first or short okay and ultimately price comes you know this is the first
sign of weakness when price poked past there although it's coming into a fractal
it draws back up this extension leg okay we extend it past these lows a bit of a
response ultimately we come into the apex base bottom okay and then price runs
again on the downside which is showing us that there's not enough liquidity
inside here or here for buyers to continue pushing which is only telling us you know
so there's a weaker but sorry buyers are weaker sellers are taking control price run came to the
bottom side this time and then again it runs but this time okay we've got a few
responses here at the clean breaking point at the point of release near the
liquidity base top there as well but ultimately it runs to retest the high okay
right at the apex but then again it takes another price run down in this
instance we already consumed the top the middle and the bottom of the shelf
moving all the by side liquidity out the way also they couldn't
push past whatever cell-side liquidity was picked up here at daily level and you know
it's no surprise then price actually started to gap slip through that level okay
volatility is a function of liquidity this is a full price one there's a liquidity base
there's a pick-up at the top price runs price pause continuation leg apex
consolidation parabolic phase um apex base retest and then we come for a shelf bottom
retest again it forms another apex base retest goes in a run
Also, if you were looking at this, yes, this is a broader price run, okay?
We could also zoom in to price.
This will be a mini fractal base.
It goes and runs to the high, picks up sellers.
This would also be a mini shelf, okay?
Again, price invalidated the shelf this time.
So in this instance, if the price is invalidated to the shelf and it draws back in for
apex retested this particular fractal cell base, again, that is a very tradable.
something I'd like to trade. So if I was to put this into context, right, these trades there,
there, of course there, maybe there, okay? When we flip beneath this inventory, price
invalidated it, drew back in for apex retest, trade there, trade at that high, invalidates,
comes back in, trade on this apex retest. Basically, the point making is these fucking
countless trades, you can find all of these particular price behaviors and engage them.
Okay, there's just so many exercises.
And this is probably like the duration of a week.
You have the exact same price runs on the lower time frame.
They're not all as clean as this, but generally speaking, the definition is there.
All the constituent parts of price rooms there as well.
They can happen at different times.
Just like this is a gap slip past these eyes.
We had a gap slip here past these lows, you know, into voids the liquidity.
So there's a void of liquidity here, so price accelerates through.
There's a void of liquidity here.
the price accelerates through now that's not only it as well you know there's a price
response here the point of release ish and price comes to the bottom side and it goes
in a price run this is the shelf this time on the downside okay price come on on the way down
this was forming the shelf the bottom side was picked okay when we picked up the pickup
at the bottom run put in the low there the first touch trade there ultimately then price
comes okay we're gonna be really really technical about it the bottom side was
picked it comes and consumes the rest of the liquidity inside of this shelf there
and again it's absorbed inside the apex retest okay so ultimately comes
towards the apex retest region ideally I would have wanted to extend this
for the six to extend a bit lower but again it goes in a run into no man's land
the nature of this move higher because of how far it's traveled is pretty is
trying down liquidity comes into a small breakout accumulation fractal there and again it goes
in a price run down but there's liquidity base high apex price pause continuation
leg gap slip we tested the apex base and this is then forming an overall
liquidity base but this price movement that actually ended up happening late in the day
okay let's look at another example very this so this is picking up a h1 level okay this is the
inventory of cell side liquidity but we can already see the bottom was pick the middle
and the top okay so that's what we would call
Before we reach down here, this whole shelf was picked at the bottom, the middle, and the top, and then extended.
That's something that we call a shelf wash extension.
Okay, but this whole area is drained in sell-side liquidity.
If there's no sellers there, price will ultimately move through it.
So the first touch trade, I'd be looking to run it past that shelf wash extension anyway.
And again, the more you engage, the more effective you're going to become are identifying and seeing these small variations and differences in real time.
Also, you know, you're going to develop parameters for a shelf wash extension.
I like to want it right past the shell, especially if there's like, you know, a fractal there.
And again, you know, I look to take some equity out on that trade on the first touch trade.
That doesn't mean that I can't take that trade again and I can't take that trade again.
In what instance would I take these retest trades?
I would definitely look for an apex base like retest here.
Okay, or the bottom in this instance, the apex base was already picked up.
The middle was picked up, so it came towards the bottom.
In this instance, the only time I would look or I would be confident in taking these retest trades
is because of a few variables present in price.
This has to be picking up a nice level.
Let's just say of H4 or H1 level.
Of course, the nature of the moved down should be weak, compounded as well.
So the weakness is confluent with the fact that the cell side inventory was washed,
that all of it was picked up so there's two variables here we have to be picking up a thick enough level
and the move down should be really really weak okay it should be running thinner and thinner
it should be quite extended um and if i've got a shelf wash extension there that's just like
you know the cherry on top of the cake it responds then in what instance would i take the retest
okay the variable for that would be we have to have picked up a nice level
and price has either consumed all of the shelf or better yet it's invalidated above it okay
because if there was enough sellers inside here to continue pushing you would have continued pushing
but the level was drained so price poked past it which caused a mini shift in the state or
it gives a sign that the cell side liquidity is running thin it comes right back down for a retest
okay maybe the trade there if you missed that this is definitely a trade at the unfilled liquidity
are at the liquidity base bottom.
So liquidity base top, middle, and bottom,
which also does coincide in this instance
with a point of release.
Okay, it released from that point.
So in what instances would I be taking the retest
after prices and validated the shelf?
That's when I'm looking for that retest.
So I'm not an example of that.
So we looked at this particular example
in the last video, I think,
or the one with a,
The one discussing when shelves are very close to price.
This is the shelf price.
Extended efficiently, you know, price pause, continuation leg,
consolidation leg, consolidation apex,
inefficient extension, fractal apex base, okay?
It invalidates the shelf and it draws back in.
It comes in to pick up whatever remaining liquidity there is inside.
This particular price pause runs back high for apex retest.
You bet there's an extension.
So if this was a higher timeframe,
is an extension trade here a price extended past these lows really inefficiently comes towards
the point of release okay which happens to be at the liquidity base top okay point release when
liquidity base top when they're very close together combined with a really weak leg in towards
this particular pocket i like those trades okay so price extended and efficiently generates
a response right back into the apex so if we look at the broader state liquidity liquidity
high okay this is a full price swing where the buyer should have held okay
inside there continued pushing price actually poked past it rendering that whole
level weak and washed okay so if the buy inventory is weakening price goes to
the weaker side we need a few variables and factors that we need to take these
trades course this should have picked up a decent enough level extended
pastising ship okay this price run has had all the features of the you know
So the run already, the apex consolidation is present, and then on top of that, we've
been validated beneath the apex slash the shelf.
So when you have these invalidations, IDD, the shelf will be close, okay, close to the apex.
We don't really want it to be too far away.
When the shelf is a bit further away from price, okay, which you can have a look at next.
So when the shelf is a bit further away from price, like in this instance, then, you know,
if price extends really inefficient into that shelf and look for a response, but in this instance,
price just sat on it, okay?
We clearly seen sellers pressure the liquidity inside, you know, the shelf, okay?
So there wasn't any great responses for us to take because the way price was moving into
the level wasn't favorable, it was actually giving signs that sellers are strong, okay?
we want for the if we're gonna if you want a response on the buy side here yes we know
there's a massive liquidity but we want a weak my a weakening massive sellers coming
into that level price goes to the weaker side okay also another thing to point out
here is this was the first high this was the shell price invalidated it came
into pretty much nowhere and then there was a bit of a pop which actually invalidated
the height again you know if I was to have gone short here or here I
got stopped out or even a buy exercise that got stopped out but that doesn't necessarily
invalidate the trade idea because of this broader state of liquidity price already came into no man's
land telling us that the buyers where they should have held up where they should have held up
on there anymore and then we had this really really really weak inefficient extension which further left
it vulnerable that's why part of my process is identifying the paint trade if i'm looking to go
short here I've already considered and asked myself what will I do if price extends past
this high and fix the most pain takes my stop but then ultimately goes in my
direction oh there might be a better level here the farm was picked maybe it's
come to the top side okay that just limits surprises okay you so you don't want to be
surprised we want to be tracking liquidity we want to be looking at the state of
liquidity inside the shelves the broader price run and what price might do okay
not really gonna make this video too long there's just one last example of a
shelf wash extension that I want to show okay there's a good long now this was the
border shell which is now this time further weight in price okay so we had the
high we came into this apex breakout level price comes invalidates this
small fractal comes and picks up the top side of the shell response comes in
for apex retest potential at a short there and then it goes all the way down to
the bottom of the shell, confluent with a point of release this time near the bottom of the
liquidity base, okay? And then it goes, actually, it starts to extend past these highs and
validating any short set-ups inside here. Rather, it pushes to new liquidity, unfield liquidity
past these highs, okay? Yes, this high would have been annoying. It would have been really painful
because, you know, if you're short here, you just want price to break down. Okay, but if we look at
the broader context this actually comes into a residual base okay these are
all residual base price goes to the feeder of these two highs okay so this
height ping off the bottom side of a base ping off the bottom of the
bottom side this goes to the top side of the base okay and again the more you
engage the better you're going to become in anticipating which one of these
variations is going to be present in price or likely to a growing price
especially when you're seeing how price extended here,
how it failed to hold inside here and continue down, okay?
You're really going to be questioning yourself, okay, is this how you can hold?
The more you engage, the more examples you see, naturally, they'll become internalized.
But your price came to the bottom side, picked it up, run it.
What's happened?
The biceide liquidity is picked up here, the top side of the shelf, the bottom, run as well,
extended away.
The same pattern is present here.
This is the shelf.
we invalidate it coming to pretty you know coming to a shitty little fractal there and run
that away as well invalidating this high by that point this whole area is running dry
person high responds fractal can't push past this closest bit of cell side inventory
and it goes in a price run ultimately even even further down okay so when it comes to
exercising okay you want to be identifying key features of these price runs okay
where there may be trades explaining them first of all through the principles of liquidity that we're
applying so this leaves residual liquidity behind the shelf you know if there's a bulk of liquidity
in the shelf and prices coming into them inefficiently you know it's going to generate a response
price goes to the weaker side if the top and the bottom of the shelf is picked and it's extended
away next time become price are likely to trade straight through it or not find too much trouble
trading through it so relate the particular features that you're engaging with the
principles and liquidity that we're applying to the market okay and then you want to
basically see that if you can find trade using these particular features and
generate a positive expectancy okay where you the more time you take that trade
that specific trade setup it could be the top of the shelf bottom retest when
and price comes in efficiently, okay,
if that actually generates a potential positive expectancy
for that set-up, okay?
And what that would be is a counterflow set up.
So if we just go, look at a real chart on cable,
like this, for example, on Friday,
price extends down into the unflow liquidity.
In this instance, the shelf is further away from price,
okay?
The shelf is further away from price.
Price extends inefficiently into the unflow
liquidity inside the shelf it picked the top and released so we price
basically came to the farm side of that fractal okay extended and efficiently
and it's generated a well a 30-pip response nearly okay and probably would
mind when we open up we could go for a bigger response so the point I'm making
here is in this is that you're trading against the flows right prices
already put in the high is invalidated the apex it's come right back in for the
Apex retest, oh, that's definitely a short as well. Short there, short there, because price
got past the shell. And the examples that we looked at earlier in this recording. Now,
easily, in this instance, it could have extended to new highs. Yes, it could have, but it didn't,
right? We just have to be willing to, you know, be willing to be wrong, accept that you might
be wrong, and trade the probabilities in price. The more you engage this specific feature,
you will identify specific variations and variables that you like that actually compound the probabilities
in your favor that doesn't mean it's definitive but if you know the probability is higher take that
trade over and over you'll have a positive expectancy you will see that trade work out more times
than it doesn't okay rather than price holding in this level for example building up why would you
are short there right we want to see some kind of weakness price and validate the shelf
if it's picking up a nice level
and if it comes back in
you know there's a short bit
if you gauged it properly
now in this instance
we extended and efficiently
the shift has occurred
as in the state of liquidity
has shifted where buyers have
you know start to withdraw from the market
hence why price is bleeding back in
to find more buyers
and the way this extended down
left this leg vulnerable
and that generates a 30-pip response
and actually for these trades
when I'm trading against the broader state of equity when I'm trading against the
flows which is down in this instance I'd be looking to close those trades
quickly take equity quickly but I would still take that trade okay sometimes
price will just sit on that level and trade through it and let's say I've taken
along here then and price isn't responding it's actually clustering and
clustering and clustering then you bet I'm gonna take I'm likely to close that
trade I'll show you an example of it this is a broader shelf
Okay, the top side was picked, so we retest, extended, flip the apex base, comes down.
Now this is extending really inefficiently into the bottom side of the shell, but it's not generating a big enough response.
What happens is you respond, comes to the clean breaking point in the closest cell side fractal,
and ultimately from there it sits, it sits, it sits, it sits for hours overnight.
Okay, this response and the anatomy of that response is very, very, very different to the response that we got here.
Okay, so all depends on how price leaves that level as well.
How can I differentiate in real time?
The more you exercise in a very structured way,
so defining what feature you're exercising,
defining what kind of setup it is,
whether you're trading with the flow against the flow, the time frame,
you know, the better you're going to get ultimately differentiating
between when it's a loser,
generate a positive expectancy for that trade.
And even you start to internalize trades that are shit.
Okay, well that means is if this, you take this trade,
and every single time so for example you try to buy this breakout or pass these highs and every time
you do it it always comes back on you when you go into drawdown you're actually starting to
internalize that this is a shit sell and you won't ever want to risk real money on it the problem is
when you try to do it with real money you're not actually learning anymore you want it to make money
and you know it does generate really bad psychological effects so internalizing negative
expectancy trades is good because you know what not to do
and you know what winners or what losers look like,
but trying to do it with real money,
you'll start to really damage a psychological profile
when looking at trading.
Yeah, that's it for this video.
Next we'll start to discuss gap slips like this.
The clean breaking points,
our price can come to clean breaking points and respond,
especially if they're close to a liquidity base,
all there's a fractal inside liquidity base.
But yeah, we'll do that in due time.
If any questions, let me know.